I'm very excited to do this interview I
first I was a TV journalist for many
years I worked for Channel 4 News
and I first covered psychedelic therapy
back in 2008 with Michael MIT offers
work with MDMA therapy and so I've been
watching this at this area for a long
time and being very excited about it and
it feels like I remember when your New
Yorker article came out 2014 yeah and I
remember thinking that was a really
seminal moment that a writer I just do a
short introduction to you you're you're
an author of many New York Times
bestseller books and were were rated one
of the hundred most influential people
by Time magazine in 2010 but it's fair
to say that you're you're a very
successful writer and it's it's
wonderful to see a man to see you go
into this area where do you sense this
conversation is at cuz I I felt for a
while like psychedelic therapy is
something that is coming into the
mainstream yeah I think that's right and
and on the evidence of my book tour and
the publication of his book and the
response to this book the culture seems
to be at an inflection point and things
are changing and that there is an
openness to this topic that I didn't
expect to find the fact that the
mainstream media has expressed so much
interest in this the fact that I'm
talking to audiences who were not
Psychonauts really mainstream audiences
and they're all ears and I think that
owes a lot to the the research being
done on therapeutic applications I think
that a lot of people are suffering out
there there's a tremendous problem with
depression and suicide and addiction and
they're very few tools available to the
mental health community and and so the
the openness hunger for a new one that
might you know that showing some promise
is I think really galvanizing the
interest so if the New Yorker article
was kind of a seminal moment surely the
book is even more of a seminal moment
yeah we'll see I mean you know history
will tell but so far the
the book has has flabbergasted me I mean
that it's been so positive and and that
we didn't know if your average book
reader or my average reader would want
to buy a book on psychedelics people
don't know how to do that they know how
to book a buy a book about food or
nature you know the other topics I've
written about but he was one that was
you know we just didn't know that there
would be people would be comfortable
owning a book about psychedelics let
alone reading it and but it appears they
are and and some of it is because it's
not just a book on psychedelics it's
really a book about the mind and what
psychedelics teaches us about the mind
which is quite extraordinary and the
mind as it works in in in people who are
well and the mind as it doesn't work in
people who are struggling with mental
illness so you know I think a lot of
people are interested for that reason
because they are struggling and but I'm
amazed also at how many people read the
book or come hear a talk and are clearly
very excited about the possibility of
doing saying they may never have done
before and it I haven't filled a sense
of responsibility about that but it's
very interesting that people once they
read about this they they have a they
feel they have to go through a thought
process do I want to do this or do I not
want to do this you know I read lots of
books where I don't go through that
thought process do I want to climb
Everest or not climbing over I don't
even think about it I'm interesting
because I read cooked book about food
and I started doing fermentor yeah but
that was my goal is to inspire people to
do things they wouldn't ordinarily do
and and maybe that's something about my
work that it could be it I don't know
that people do want to do this stuff
that I described so but I you know
there's a sense of responsibility that
goes with that because it's not for
everyone and people do run into trouble
and when the drugs are used carelessly
people have kidnapped real psychological
trials and so I you know I'm just
concerned that people approach it with
the kind of momenta sness that I
it was a big deal and I was you know I
didn't go easily into this world I had I
had lots of reluctance I had to overcome
I was very reluctant psychonaut because
it's interesting when I first heard that
you were writing about this I thought he
must be an old hippie and he's kind of
but it that's not the case at all when I
read the book and listened to a podcast
I had very little experience and no I
had had no major psychedelic experience
I had had a couple I've heard hear
people refer to as museum doses of
psilocybin or aesthetic doses you know
which are you know not I mean like
smoking cannabis or something like that
but you know the full-blown ego
dissolving psychedelic trip no I didn't
have that till I was nearly 60 because
can you tell me a bit about that it's
quite interesting from a cultural
perspective that you didn't quite get
the first 60s way you got more of the
the backlash against it is that is that
first yeah I grew up I came of age the
the moment at which I would even think
about taking a psychedelic would have
been you know 68 to 70 and this is in
the this is in the full flowering of
this panic that hit especially in
America but I think it was true here too
and in America you know psychedelics got
left the laboratory and got you know
embraced by the counterculture and it
was many straight people and older
people thought that it was fueling the
reluctance of American boys to go to
Vietnam and yeah oh I'm sure it was I
mean there was something very
anti-authoritarian about the the gist of
the experience people were having they
were questioning all authorities and all
games were looked at as games and
whether that was inherent in the
molecule or just the context in which
was being taken we don't really know but
certainly President Nixon saw it as a
big threat he called Timothy Leary who
already was like a washed-up psychology
professor he called him the most
dangerous man in America because he was
urging everybody to turn on tune in and
drop out and people were doing that lots
of people were dropping out they were
washing up in haight-ashbury or going to
you know communes in
Northern California and Tennessee and it
was a very disruptive time and to some
people this was incredibly exciting and
it and it did help create the world we
live in now environmental movement
feminism I mean the way we eat all these
things are sixties products but to many
people it was terrifying and and the gap
in particular between the young and the
old was really emphasized by LSD and
experience that the young were having a
rite of passage the young were having
that the the elders did not understand
and that's not usually how it works with
rites of passage usually they knit a
society together this was a weird one so
it was so I was hearing all the scare
stories I was hearing about you know
people staring at the Sun till they go
blind or the guy who had so much orange
sunshine he thought he was an orange for
the rest of his life and you know there
were like crazy stories but there were
true stories too there were you know
people doing stupid horror stories of
what what came out towards the end of
the 60s as well ya know the scene got
very dark and sour and and that's what I
in baibe was like wow LSD you're you
know you're playing Russian roulette
with your brain and and I also didn't
feel psychologically sturdy enough to
withstand such an assault or what I
thought would be such an assault so you
think you were right to think that I
think probably I was certainly in my
teen years maybe in my 20s would be
different you know and people have asked
me do I regret not having done it then
and I don't really I don't know how
things would have been different had I
done it and as I say in the book I
really think they have special value
actually when you get older you know I
said there's kind of a throwaway line in
the book that psychedelics may be wasted
on the young and I know that's unfair
cuz a lot of young people have had very
important transformative experiences but
I think they're particularly valuable
when you're more set in your ways and
you have all this material all this life
behind you to process and figure out and
all these issues that have formed and
your thought patterns have have gotten
rigid
you know you're in your deep in your
grooves of how you respond to any given
situation you have these very handy
mental algorithms but they also are a
trap and and psychedelics can spring you
from that trap sort of some sense in
spirituality at least you need a strong
ego to be able to yeah to go beyond it
and that's a real question about you
know people who are fifteen or sixteen
don't yet have a fully formed you go and
and so what does it mean to have an ego
dissolving experience at that point I
don't know I mean and actually maybe
they're not having that experience maybe
they're having more of a museum
experience it's it's more of an outward
experience for people who are doing it
recreationally I use that word advisedly
because I because it sounds dismissive
and I don't mean it that way at all but
the kind of experience people are having
in the therapeutic context or in the
underground guided context is a very
internal experience you're wearing eye
shades you're listening to music you're
not just getting off on the sensory
information coming in with the exception
of the music and that's a substantially
different experience it's a much more
psychoanalytic experience really you
yeah its internal and you're processing
the people in your lives the things
you've done your belief system and I
don't think that's how an 18 year old
uses it it's interesting as well I've
heard I think it was the Sam Harris
podcast where you talked about your sort
of spiritual beliefs or perhaps lack of
spiritual beliefs going into it
because very interesting I'd read cooked
and in defense of food and what I found
in it in defense of food in particular
was was a sort of mysticism of the
natural world in that there's a
skepticism about what you called kind of
nutritionism yeah productiveness of
science yes exactly reductive scientific
materialism of it somehow
removes the ineffable quality of your
food for example so would you say that's
an accurate description the natural mr.
Simonet it's not it's a critique of
science and the way science goes about
understanding something like flow we
didn't
it fails to see it sees food as a pile
of chemicals which is not a very fulsome
description of food because food in
addition to being having nutrients has a
structure and that structure is very
important it also is a set of
relationships right when you eat your
your connecting to the to the natural
world to the earth to the to the species
you're eating to other people it's a
communal experience so a so it's an
argument I don't know if it's a mystical
argument but it's an argument for the
more holistic way of thinking about it
and I mean people read that book and
botany of desire and see spirituality in
it and and the fact that in botany of
desire
you know the subtitle is a plants I view
of the world there's a lot of
imaginative effort to see things from
the plants point of view but to me that
was kind of an intellectual conceit
after my psychedelic experiences it
became like a very firmly held oh my god
that's all true they do have
subjectivity I can feel it there
regarding me in some sense the plants so
but but but I think the main thing that
happened was my understanding of what
spirituality was shifted I had always
thought that spiritual the opposite of
spiritual was material and if he
believed in the spiritual it meant you
believed in the supernatural or the
mystical saying which most people assume
means supernatural and I've never been
prepared to give up on the laws of
nature and that that everything you know
nature is everything that there is and
we may not understand it all but there's
there's you don't transcend it and but I
but what I learned through these
experiences that were incredibly
powerful and there were all experiences
of connection connection to nature
connection to people in my life the
feelings of love I had for my wife and
my son and my sisters and my mother and
father I realized that those that the
essence of spirituality to me at least
and obviously can be different for
different people was that overwhelmingly
powerful connection and that what keeps
us from feeling that connection in
ordinary hours and days
is is the ego and the defenses of the
ego and the fact that the brain is tuned
to novelty rather than the familiar - I
think that hides that hides important
things from us because we're our brains
are always looking for changes in the
environment as well they should it's
very adaptive but it misses a lot it
blinds us to important things so I
realized the opposite of spiritual is
not the material it's egotistical and to
the extent you can transcend your ego
you will have spiritual experiences and
they're right at hand you know it's just
about your perspective there's plenty of
wonder without stipulating a beyond so
anyway it may be an inadequate
definition of spiritual for some people
but I now I feel much more comfortable
in that camp a spiritual person yeah I
guess that you could it's more kind of
expanding the concept of what
materialism is that's right rather
dismiss right oh yeah are denying it or
video yeah yes exactly and that there's
plenty of wonder right here in the in
this room yeah and what would you how do
you sum up how you were changed by this
journey this right in this book well in
that way that was a very important
change in my understanding of what
mattered and how the world worked so
that was a big deal
I think as a result I mean the big thing
that happened to me is acquiring a
little bit more distance or fresh
perspective on my ego and realizing I
don't have to identify with it all the
time and that it is a tool and it gets
up to some tricks I don't like and I
don't always have to listen to that
voice and there are other voices and
that sounds crazy you know if you were a
psychiatrist that's not what I mean
but that there's another ground on which
to stand
besides ego consciousness and that it's
it's hard to reach that other ground
I had a glimpse of it during at least
one of my psychedelic experiences but it
is something you can cultivate through
meditation through recognizing when your
defenses are springing into gear that no
that's what that is and you know there
are other ways to get there than
psychedelics you know people get there
through psychotherapy but it happened
much faster and psychedelics so that's
been really valuable change if you ask
my wife she would say that she thinks
I'm much more open much more comfortable
talking about emotional topics less
defensive so yeah she was very worried
at the beginning that I would change in
ways that you know she I mean she she
she had trepidations about it cuz you
know we'd been together a long time in
here I was having a big experience that
she wasn't having that hasn't happened
you know we had a kid together all these
all the big experiences in our lives we
did together death was deaf parents and
things like that but here was one I was
gonna go off on my own and she was very
concerned about it but in the end what
she didn't consider that I might change
for the better right and she said it I
have so what were you most excited to
discover during writing the book oh so
much I mean the neuroscience was
fascinating to learn about and it was
something I knew nothing about I really
hadn't studied the brain in any way I
didn't I wasn't someone who read books
on neuroscience or consciousness studies
and and all that what we're learning
what psychedelics teaching us about the
brain is incredible and the mind I mean
I really do see it as a tool and you
know there's this outrageous quote from
stanislav grof from years ago in the 60s
he said that psychedelics would be for
the study of the mind what what the
telescope was for that for astronomy and
what the microscope was for biology and
you know that was really an outrageous
thing to say David not saying the same
thing yeah yeah and Robin Carhartt
Harris too and so I don't think it's
crazy anymore and it's taught me a lot
about the mind
and so the study of psychedelics and
psychedelics themselves are teaching us
really valuable things about the mind
that was thrilling the history was
thrilling I had no idea what was going
on before Timothy Leary before the 1960s
that there was this very fertile period
of research all through the 50s where
interesting discoveries were being made
and incredible characters were were
roaming the stage of history that have
been completely forgotten people like Al
Hubbard and Humphry Osmond and so that
one said well yeah Hollingshead Sidney
Cohen and la Betsey Eisner in LA I mean
these names are not known to people but
they're really interesting characters
doing very serious work and it's like
Timothy Leary has taken up all the
oxygen in the room and and it's a shame
I mean his story is very interesting and
I'm I take pains to tell it in a new way
but but the fact is they're their
characters even more interesting than he
is and so as a writer I had a very it
was a really exciting period of
discovery I mean you know usually when
you write a book like some chapters
you're really excited about and some you
just have to get from point A to point B
I never had that feeling here every
chapter I was I was finding a new world
and it was an undiscovered world and so
it was it was a thrill actually to write
and then the trip you know writing about
my own trips I'd never written
I'd never I mean I'm a nonfiction writer
I'm a journalist I I'm used to working
in this very tight constraint of these
this box of facts that can all be fact
checked and here I was writing about
saying that was the pure product of my
imagination and I imagine it's it's kind
of what a novelist does you know that
they they have to hear dialogue they
have a movie running in their heads that
they're writing writing down and then
maybe an overly simplistic way to look
at it but I so I was in that space and
as a writer that was even though I had a
lot of trepidations about how can you
make a trip interesting it's such an
internal thing and it's you know isn't
it like a dream who's interested in
other people's dreams I'm certainly not
but as it turns out it's not like a
dream in many ways it's much more
concrete
much more kind of narrative li coherent
and writing about that was turned out to
be a thrill I mean it was kind of the
Everest in the middle of the book that I
kept my gone right now I got to get to
this part and how am I gonna get up this
mountain but once I found the voice in
which to do it which took a little doing
and a few false starts it was great fun
and whether I succeeded obviously for
the reader to decide but so yeah so as a
writing project this was fantastic as a
learning project was fantastic and as a
personal project I had a lot of skin in
this game you know this wasn't it just a
cool journalistic inquiry their chapters
that are that but then their chapters
where I'm kind of you know I've gotta
you know I'm putting myself into this
situation
a situation that I had a lot of
reluctance about that was very and it
was very exposing and this is definitely
my most personal book and there wasn't a
way to do it without just saying well
don't you can't worry about how you look
you just have to be truthful to the
experience there's a sense as well I
mean you you've you've got a lot of
credibility from your previous work from
your food work and I guess this area we
talk about kind of synchronicity or we
talk about kind of there being some
greater meaning to to what's going on is
there a sense that you were meant to
write this book do you do you have any
any sympathy with that no I don't I mean
other people could have written this
book you know I was lucky it was lucky I
stumbled on when I did I do realize now
that for many people I was the right
messenger I didn't write it thinking
that I mean as a writer I don't think
that I have this this bag of credibility
I can bring and distribute over other
topics I feel you have to earn your
credibility your authority as a writer
every every book every article you can't
if you just write because I'm so-and-so
and you know and that's that's not how
you readers are not interested in that I
mean that's speechifying that's
lecturing and that's not what I do I
started from the beginning and mastered
this topic but I realized too many
readers as
like Michael Pollan's writing about this
it must not be too crazy he didn't leave
me wrong on on food there was a woman I
did an event at Google
in Seattle and this woman stood up and
she's like in her 30s you know a coder
or something like that very successful
and she said you know I read Omnivore's
Dilemma and I had to learn how to how to
slaughter and butcher a pig and I had no
idea as I was driving to work today that
now I would have to take LSD so I you
know I told her she didn't have to take
us tea maybe she wants to learn how to
meditate there are other ways to achieve
these states of consciousness but yeah I
guess some people feel that way about
what I write do you have any concerns
because there is something there is a
sort of question as to whether the
psychedelic experience is a natural fit
for the scientific method or for the
medical method you have any sort of
concerns there's something kind of
almost ungraspable or ineffable about
the experience yeah that that's proven a
difficult fit with both of those models
in the past without question I mean how
do you control a psychedelic trial can
you really control it and no and not
know who's got the got the psychedelic
and who didn't you know some of the
researchers say they've successfully
fooled even their their their therapy
their guides as to who got the drug and
who got the act of placebo it's a it's
it's a it's a challenge to science in
many ways and you know I was having a
conversation with Mike day who's Mike
Jay I'm sorry he's written a lot about
this and and he he believes that
psychedelics have taught us more about
science then science have taught us
about psychedelics I'm not sure I agree
with him but I see his point that you
really see the limitations and you see
how limited our understanding of the
mind is and that these are complicated
chemicals because they're not consistent
in their effects yeah and you have a
method that's designed to extract
meaning out or or a limit variables and
how do you limit if you if set and
setting are so important how do you
assure that every one is only having an
experience of the molecule in fact the
therapist who gave it to them
was given in a chalice or in a cup paper
cup all these things are priming the
experience and so we have to realize
that to the extent that it there the
scientific method applies it's a little
bit dirty in this case I'm not dirty but
you know it's it's it's definitely a
challenge to limit the number of
variables the way you need to to really
test a drug is difficult and in many
other and many other aspects too but
that doesn't mean we shouldn't do it
it's it's the best standard or the best
system we have for showing the safety
and efficacy of a drug before we admit
it to modern medicines so it may not be
perfect the method we have and it may
not be you know exactly right for this
substance but it's what we have
mmm my concern when so I've done a
couple of couple of pieces one for news
night BBC Newsnight maybe two years ago
was that I still have concerns that
there might be too much enthusiasm but
at the moment what the journalists have
been writing about this and the people
have been featuring it are also to a
degree
psychedelic enthusiasts I mean I
certainly was was sold on the idea of it
being positive and there's a kind of
self-selecting we're selecting people
who are already enthusiastic so I do
have some concerns that we could we
could recreate yeah over sell or
recreate some of the kind of over in
exuberance of the night I I detect
everybody trying to keep a lid on that
and the researchers certainly but they
feel it you get them out for a drink or
beer and like this could be a revolution
of mental healthcare yeah and it could
be but it might not be and you know the
fact is it's it's important to
understand that these small trials 15 20
40 you're bound to get better results
than you're gonna get in larger trials
because you're getting to pick your
volunteers and screen out lots of people
so you're getting the people most likely
to respond you're also the therapists
the guides who are involved are very
committed to the project they're not
people you took off the street and
trained and that'll be in the next phase
you've got enthusiasts all over the
place and so that is encouraging
positive results that said the result
were so good in some cases that even if
they were half as good it would still be
better than the leading treatment we
have for anxiety and depression so yeah
I mean I wasn't a psychedelic enthusiast
when I started this the New Yorker
article I hadn't had a psychedelic
experience I was mystified by the fact
that this would work and that that
people who were dying could actually
reset their feelings about death and
overcome their fear of death after a
single psychedelic experience this was
completely beyond my you know sense of
what is possible and but yeah there is a
there's an occupational hazard it's it's
something about these drugs that people
can get irrationally exuberant
and so I think your caution is a really
important note and we should realize
that we're really still at the beginning
and there's no you know I can point to
people who whose lives have been changed
in very positive ways by these medicines
but whether it will work with a large
population we don't know yet yeah and I
guess my other concern would be that if
we're looking at it from a strictly
medical model the idea that you take
this pill and it makes you better well
it's not exactly the medical model
because it's what's really interesting
about this is it's not psychedelic
therapy it's psychedelic assisted
psychotherapy it's really the joining of
talk therapy with chemistry and so
anyway to finish your question yeah for
some people it can be a very trend you
can have a very transformative
experience a mystical experience that
that is really encouraging but for other
people what it can do is bring up an
awful lot of suppressed stuff that you
don't have to deal with there's sort of
two although that can be very
therapeutic
I mean I've talked to people who got in
touch with childhood trauma that they
were completely unaware of and work
through it so that's why the therapist
is so important you bring up things like
that and people don't know how to deal
with that I mean that's why integration
that what happens after your your your
session is probably the most important
part
and if you don't integrate well
you could leave people hanging with you
no real I mean on with real problems
suddenly this came up you know my father
abused me where do I go now this really
happened did it really happen so it's
you know that's part of the being you
know treating this process with enormous
respect and caution it's really
important there's some concern in the
psychedelic community at the moment that
there are corporate corporates coming in
and most of the research so far has been
done in the academic model so
everything's public everything's
published and now corporates are
starting to come in and there is a sense
of unease and the selected community
about that do you share that unease at
all
yeah I mean it definitely gives me cause
for concern I mean I think we're moving
to a place where people are trying to
lock up intellectual property in a
market and I think the academics have to
be very careful not to get ripped off
and you know one of the attractions to
these drugs is they're all public domain
or they should be that you're not going
to have the usual pharmaceutical model
and in fact intellectual property only
takes you so far because you really have
to figure out a way to create a whole
package you know of therapy and drug and
integration and the right kind of room
all this kind of stuff but this is the
way of the world you know on the
positive side you could say that it's
only when corporations get interested
that you can scale this up and reach
lots of people and achieve the kind of
efficiencies of scale you know so
there's that argument can be made you
know I'm not sure I mean you know my own
inclination is is there a way to do this
in a non-profit model I mean I think
Maps is doing something interesting with
a public benefit corporation as a model
but there's going to be a lot of
experimentation and no one this is this
is not an area that lends itself to
monopolies anybody can find these
mushrooms anyone can grow these
mushrooms so the ideal companies trying
to patient psilocybin
pathetic suicide venya manufacturing
method we'll see if that works it may
not work many people have made it before
making it at scale is the challenge but
still the mushroom still grows and it's
available and not hard to find so
there's a protection in that there's a
you know nature is is defending us
against nature it's nature's antitrust
act so I guess I mean this does feel as
you say like an inflection point an
inflection point for the public
awareness of this kind of these
therapies and within the community as
well yeah and there are definitely
tensions erupting around the profit mark
model versus the non profit model and no
I think we're gonna see a lot of change
and you know those tensions are a
reflection though that there's something
worth fighting over there's value here
and so you can you can look at it as
it's an index to the fact that there's
money to be made here
there's which is in itself an index to
the fact that there might be something
of value Michael Pollan thank you very
much oh my pleasure
yeah great talk